Sai Prasad Padhy

+91-9550003197 | saiprasadpadhy@gmail.com LinkedIn | GitHub

Profile

Data Engineer with 5+ years of experience building large-scale data pipelines, ETL processes, and data warehouse solutions. Utilized technologies like Python, SQL, Spark, Databricks, and ADF to develop multi-terabyte scalable big data solutions for Fortune 100 manufacturing and pharmaceutical companies.

Technical Skills

Programming Languages: Python, SQL

Big Data Technologies: Spark, PySpark, Spark SQL, YARN, Kubernetes, Hadoop, Hive, Impala

Streaming Technology: Kafka, Spark Structured Streaming

ADF, Databricks, ADLS, Amazon S3, Event Hub, Azure VM Cloud computing:

Data Engineering Tools: Azure DevOps, Data Modelling, ETL/ELT data Pipeline, Delta Lake

Orchestration: ADF, Airflow, Redwood

Familiar: FastAPI, Synapse, Microsoft Fabric

Experience

Tech Mahindra

January 2022 - Present

Hyderabad, India

Senior Data Engineer

- Led a team of 2 Data Engineers in designing, developing, and optimizing data pipelines and ETL processes.
- Developed an automated system by aggregating data from multiple sources where business can easily find reliable customers for procuring raw materials.
- Integrated and processed Procurement and shipment data from multiple sources including AWS, Azure, SQL Server, and SAP, handling various file formats like JSON, CSV, and Parquet.
- Implemented Spark optimization techniques such as caching, multithreading, broadcast joins and Delta lake optimizations, resulting in a 20% decrease in processing time for handling a daily load of around 3 Million records.

Tech Mahindra January 2022 - Present

Data Engineer

Hyderabad, India

- Migrated the entire data platform from on-prem to Azure Databricks, including code migration, code optimization, and data validation between on-premises and Databricks, achieving a 30% cost reduction.
- Designed and developed advanced scheduling capabilities using Azure Data Factory (ADF), reducing manual intervention and streamlining workflows.
- Developed a robust framework to handle data from various file formats, including CSV, Excel, JSON, and Parquet, with support for multiple load types such as full, append, and merge.

Cognizant

June 2019 - January 2022

Data Engineer Chennai, India

- Delivered a project to migrate legacy on-premise processes to the cloud using Big Data technologies (Spark), reducing processing time by 20%.
- Developed Azure Data Factory pipelines to perform daily data migration from Microsoft Dynamics to SQL Server, handling approximately 40 million records across 25 tables.
- Optimized overall process performance through Spark performance tuning, improving job run times by 20% and efficiently managing a 15Terabyte(TB) dataset containing approximately 12 billion records.
- Created Power Automate, Azure functions to ingest data from SFTP, SharePoint to ADLS

EDUCATION

Lovely Professional University

Bachelor of Technology in Mechanical Engineering

Jalandhar, Punjab July 2015 - June 2019

Sri Chaitanya Junior College

Hyderabad, Telangana April 2013 - Mar 2015

Senior Secondary School